<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A.H. Fullerton | </title>
    <link>/authors/a.h.-fullerton/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/a.h.-fullerton/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>A.H. Fullerton</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 18:44:54 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>A.H. Fullerton</title>
      <link>/authors/a.h.-fullerton/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Music of Rivers: The Mathematics of Waves Reveals Global Structure and Drivers of Streamflow Regime</title>
      <link>/publication/brown_river_music/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 18:44:54 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/brown_river_music/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide to forest–water management (Chapter 3: Manging Forests for Water)</title>
      <link>/publication/fao_forest_water/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 18:44:54 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/fao_forest_water/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Water Sources in a Mountain River</title>
      <link>/project/snoqualmie/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 14:40:43 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/snoqualmie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In mountainous river basins of the Pacific Northwest, climate models predict that winter warming will result in increased precipitation falling as rain and decreased snowpack. A detailed understanding of the spatial and temporal dynamics of water sources across river networks will help illuminate climate change impacts on river flow regimes. Because the stable isotopic composition of precipitation varies geographically, variation in surface water isotope ratios indicates the volume-weighted integration of upstream source water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We measured the stable isotope ratios of surface water samples collected in the Snoqualmie River basin in western Washington over June and September 2017 and the 2018 water year. We used ordinary least squares regression and geostatistical Spatial Stream Network models to relate surface water isotope ratios to mean watershed elevation (MWE) across seasons. Geologic and discharge data was integrated with water isotopes to create a conceptual model of streamflow generation for the Snoqualmie River. We found that surface water stable isotope ratios were lowest in the spring and highest in the dry, Mediterranean summer, but related strongly to MWE throughout the year. Low isotope ratios in spring reflect the input of snowmelt into high elevation tributaries. High summer isotope ratios suggest that groundwater is sourced from low elevation areas and recharged by winter precipitation. Overall, our results suggest that baseflow in the Snoqualmie River may be resilient to predicted warming and subsequent changes to snowpack in the Pacific Northwest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research was funded by a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nwcasc.uw.edu/&#34;&gt; Northwest Climate Adaptation Science Center &lt;/a&gt; graduate research fellowship. Future research will link this information with predicted shifts in precipitation quantity and quality and water temperature data to help design restoration strategies for endangered Pacific salmon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elevation and spatial structure explain most surface-water isotopic variation across five Pacific Coast basins</title>
      <link>/publication/cross_basin_compare/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 12:07:04 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/cross_basin_compare/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface Water Isoscapes Across Basins</title>
      <link>/project/cross_basin_comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/cross_basin_comparison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Isoscapes are a framework that describe the spatial patterns in isotopic ratios across a landscape and are useful for addressing a variety of basic and applied research questions. Stable isotopes of oxygen and hydrogen can be harnessed to determine source-water contributions to streamflow on a range of spatial and temporal scales, estimate mean transit times, and understand hydrologic flow paths. Despite the widespread use of water isotope ratios in research and their potential application for predicting future flows under a changing climate or for identifying likely areas of cool water for fisheries management, few studies have compared drivers of variation in isotopic ratios at the basin scale or across basins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drivers of variation in water isotopic spatial patterns across basins must be understood before ecologically relevant and isotopically distinct water sources can be identified and this tool efficiently applied. In this study, we compare the spatial patterns of surface water isotopes across five basins within Washington and Southeastern Alaska to quantify and compare local controls on isotopic variability of surface water and to explore the utility of applying simple elevation regressions models for estimating water source across river basins. We also compare the performance of models with and without network-based spatial autocorrelation. Specifically, the objectives of our study are (1) to compare the strength with which isotope ratios vary by mean watershed elevation (MWE) across five river basins, (2) to assess and compare whether additional landscape predictors improve models of isotope ratios across basins, and (3) to explore where SNNMs might be used to improve river water isoscape generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research was funded by a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nwcasc.uw.edu/&#34;&gt; Northwest Climate Adaptation Science Center &lt;/a&gt; graduate research fellowship. Our study will provide insights for interpreting water source contributions downstream and guidance for understanding the types, advantages, and disadvantages of isoscape generation. The project is highly relevant to researchers and resource managers seeking to understand how isoscapes can be generated and used for surface water management.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
