<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R.T. Edwards | </title>
    <link>/authors/r.t.-edwards/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/r.t.-edwards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>R.T. Edwards</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 12:07:04 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>R.T. Edwards</title>
      <link>/authors/r.t.-edwards/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elevation and spatial structure explain most surface-water isotopic variation across five Pacific Coast basins</title>
      <link>/publication/cross_basin_compare/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 12:07:04 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/cross_basin_compare/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surface Water Isoscapes Across Basins</title>
      <link>/project/cross_basin_comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/cross_basin_comparison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Isoscapes are a framework that describe the spatial patterns in isotopic ratios across a landscape and are useful for addressing a variety of basic and applied research questions. Stable isotopes of oxygen and hydrogen can be harnessed to determine source-water contributions to streamflow on a range of spatial and temporal scales, estimate mean transit times, and understand hydrologic flow paths. Despite the widespread use of water isotope ratios in research and their potential application for predicting future flows under a changing climate or for identifying likely areas of cool water for fisheries management, few studies have compared drivers of variation in isotopic ratios at the basin scale or across basins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drivers of variation in water isotopic spatial patterns across basins must be understood before ecologically relevant and isotopically distinct water sources can be identified and this tool efficiently applied. In this study, we compare the spatial patterns of surface water isotopes across five basins within Washington and Southeastern Alaska to quantify and compare local controls on isotopic variability of surface water and to explore the utility of applying simple elevation regressions models for estimating water source across river basins. We also compare the performance of models with and without network-based spatial autocorrelation. Specifically, the objectives of our study are (1) to compare the strength with which isotope ratios vary by mean watershed elevation (MWE) across five river basins, (2) to assess and compare whether additional landscape predictors improve models of isotope ratios across basins, and (3) to explore where SNNMs might be used to improve river water isoscape generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research was funded by a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nwcasc.uw.edu/&#34;&gt; Northwest Climate Adaptation Science Center &lt;/a&gt; graduate research fellowship. Our study will provide insights for interpreting water source contributions downstream and guidance for understanding the types, advantages, and disadvantages of isoscape generation. The project is highly relevant to researchers and resource managers seeking to understand how isoscapes can be generated and used for surface water management.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
