<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>E.A. Steel | </title>
    <link>/authors/e.a.-steel/</link>
      <atom:link href="/authors/e.a.-steel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>E.A. Steel</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 18:44:54 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>E.A. Steel</title>
      <link>/authors/e.a.-steel/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empirical stream thermal sensitivity cluster on the landscape according to geology and climate</title>
      <link>/publication/air_water_temperature/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 18:44:54 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/air_water_temperature/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A guide to forest–water management (Chapter 3: Manging Forests for Water)</title>
      <link>/publication/fao_forest_water/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2021 18:44:54 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/fao_forest_water/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Water Sources in a Mountain River</title>
      <link>/project/snoqualmie/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2020 14:40:43 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/snoqualmie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In mountainous river basins of the Pacific Northwest, climate models predict that winter warming will result in increased precipitation falling as rain and decreased snowpack. A detailed understanding of the spatial and temporal dynamics of water sources across river networks will help illuminate climate change impacts on river flow regimes. Because the stable isotopic composition of precipitation varies geographically, variation in surface water isotope ratios indicates the volume-weighted integration of upstream source water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We measured the stable isotope ratios of surface water samples collected in the Snoqualmie River basin in western Washington over June and September 2017 and the 2018 water year. We used ordinary least squares regression and geostatistical Spatial Stream Network models to relate surface water isotope ratios to mean watershed elevation (MWE) across seasons. Geologic and discharge data was integrated with water isotopes to create a conceptual model of streamflow generation for the Snoqualmie River. We found that surface water stable isotope ratios were lowest in the spring and highest in the dry, Mediterranean summer, but related strongly to MWE throughout the year. Low isotope ratios in spring reflect the input of snowmelt into high elevation tributaries. High summer isotope ratios suggest that groundwater is sourced from low elevation areas and recharged by winter precipitation. Overall, our results suggest that baseflow in the Snoqualmie River may be resilient to predicted warming and subsequent changes to snowpack in the Pacific Northwest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research was funded by a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nwcasc.uw.edu/&#34;&gt; Northwest Climate Adaptation Science Center &lt;/a&gt; graduate research fellowship. Future research will link this information with predicted shifts in precipitation quantity and quality and water temperature data to help design restoration strategies for endangered Pacific salmon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
